なんば　むった
Hello? Aunt Sharon?
シャロンおばちゃん！
あっ…ちょっと！
Hey!
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ｼｬﾛﾝ)
あ～ ごめんなさい｡
ケータイ 落としちゃった｡
Oh, I'm sorry! I dropped my phone...
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)あっ…ビックリした？
ケータイがキズだらけで｡
Oh, you noticed that my phone is scratched?
No...
(せりか)あっ いや…｡
なんか よく落としちゃうのよね
最近 手に力が入んなくて…｡
I keep dropping it.
It's like I just lose all strength in my hand.
ハッ！そんな…｡
No...
もう いいの？
はい｡
Is that all?
Yes...
シャロンさん…明日 朝から
もう一度 病院へ行きましょう｡
Sharon,
you should go to a hospital again in the morning.
今度は神経内科へ…｡
You should see a neurologist.
Huh?
どうこう
私も…同行します｡
I'll accompany you.
《なんだよ…!?》
What's going on?
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#64 Piece of Cake
《ん…だめだ 集中しろ！
このテストは重要だ！➡
This isn't working.
I can't concentrate...
This test is important... I should know that.
わかってんのか!?
このテストは重要!!》
This test is important.
《ここで いい点とって…
誰よりも早く…➡
I have to get a high score,
誰よりも先に
選ばれないと だめだ!!》
so I can hurry and reach the moon first!
Otherwise...
《でないと…》
I will reach the moon before Hibito.
⦅日々人より先に月に行って
｢シャロン望遠鏡｣を建てるよ⦆
And I'll build the Sharon Telescope!
⦅わかった⦆
I understand.
《シャロンとの約束が…》
...I won't be able to keep my promise to Sharon.
シャロンさんの病名ですが…➡
We haven't been able to diagnose her disorder,
まだハッキリと
答えは出せません｡➡
運動神経に何らかの変化が
生じている事は確かです｡
but there is clear evidence that her nervous system has changed.
変化…？
Changed?
せいみつ
(医師)精密検査をしてもらう
必要があります｡➡
We will need to conduct a thorough examination.
シャロンさんのご家族は？
Do you have any family, Sharon?
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)妹が２人いて
１人はニューヨークに➡
Two younger sisters.
One is in New York.
もう１人は日本にいます｡
The other is in Japan.
(医師)では ここに連絡先を…｡
Then, please fill in their contact information.
はい｡
Okay.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)あっ…｡あれ？
Oh?
(医師)あ…いいです｡
私が書きますので番号を…｡
It's fine...
Just tell me, and I'll write it down.
あっ…はい｡
Sure.
(医師)今のところ シャロンさんの
容体に関しては➡
At the moment, we are unable to identify
病名など断言できる
段階ではありません｡➡
which disorder Sharon suffers from.
It's possible her muscles have atrophied due to lack of exercise.
ただの運動不足による筋力低下
というのも考えられますし…｡
Excuse me...
あの…私が心配しているのは
エーエルエス
ＡＬＳの可能性です｡
I'm concerned that it could be ALS.
When I tapped Dr. Sharon's arm,
シャロン博士の腕を叩いたら
きんせんいそくしゅうしゅく
筋線維束収縮の反応がありました｡
I observed fascicular contractions.
あなたは医者？
Are you a doctor?
４ヵ月前までは そうでした｡
I was up until four months ago.
まだ ＡＬＳと
決まったわけじゃありません｡➡
We still can't confirm that it's ALS.
これから さらに検査を続けて
もし ＡＬＳだと診断されても➡
If we run more tests and diagnose ALS,
段階的に
伝えていく必要があります｡➡
we'll need to break the news to her slowly.
とても…重い病気ですので｡
It's a very serious disease.
A serious disease...
《重い病気…》
今日は ありがとう｡
妹が来てくれることになったわ｡➡
Thank you for coming today.
My sister's on her way over now.
だから 心配しないで
訓練 頑張ってね｡
So don't worry...
Just focus on training, Mutta and Serika.
ムッタ せりかさん｡
＜いくつもの
検査予定を告げられ…➡
After multiple tests were scheduled,
Right.
自分が何らかの病気である事は➡
Sharon must have realized that she had a serious disorder.
シャロンにも
わかっていただろうが…➡
彼女は笑顔をやめなかった＞
But she never stopped smiling...
せりかさん…｡
Serika,
何なの？…ＡＬＳって？
what is ALS?
私の父が亡くなった病気です｡
It's the disease that killed my father.
手の力が うまく入らなかったり
転ぶ事が多くなったり➡
Your arms suddenly feel weak.
You begin to trip over yourself.
シャロン博士の症状が…
あまりに父と似てたので…｡
Sharon was displaying the same symptoms as my father.
The disorder affects your motor neurons,
運動ニューロンっていう
神経だけが障害を受けて➡
脳から筋肉を動かす命令が
伝わらなくなっていくんです｡
meaning that your muscles stop moving when your brain tells them to.
そのせいで 筋肉がやせて
徐々に手足が動かせなくなって➡
As a result, your muscles weaken.
Eventually, you can no longer move your arms or legs.
食べることも 話すことも…➡
You become unable to talk, eat,
自力で呼吸も
できなくなってしまいます｡
or breathe unassisted.
《シャロンが…》
Sharon...
Now, try playing the trumpet.
⦅さあ トランペットを持って
音を出して⦆
きじ
⦅しばらく 生地をねかせたら
これの登場よ！⦆
After kneading for a while, switch to these.
⦅ムッタは何でもできる
すご
あにき
凄い兄貴になりたかったのよ⦆
Mutta wanted to become an amazing big brother who could do everything.
《あの シャロンが…》
Not Sharon...
《くそっ！…わかんねぇな…➡
Damn...
I don't know the answers.
I read the manuals, but I can't remember a thing!
ちゃんと訓練教材
読んだつもりが➡
全然 頭に
入ってねぇじゃねぇか!!➡
落ち着け…！
シャロンのことは今 考えるな！》
Stay calm...
Don't think about Sharon right now!
⦅ＡＬＳは人によって
進行の速さも違って…➡
ALS progression varies from person to person.
１０年以上かけて
徐々に悪化する人もいれば➡
Some people may go ten years before symptoms worsen.
私の父のように
速い人もいます⦆
But for some, like my father, it's much faster.
⦅は…速いって？⦆
H-How fast?
⦅父は診断されてから➡
After my father's diagnosis, he lived for two years, ten months before passing away.
２年と１０ヵ月で
亡くなりました⦆
(ビンス)試験終了です｡
ペンを置いて下さい｡
The test is over. Put your pens down.
≪終わった～！≫
All done!
《ちくしょう…！》
Damn!
＜テストの結果は…最悪だった＞
My test scores were terrible.
[TV](拍手)
ひびと
(南波日々人)ハァ…｡
＜シャロンの検査から８日後…➡
Eight days after her examination ended,
ＡＬＳという診断結果が
医師から彼女に告げられた＞
the doctors told Sharon she had ALS.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)田村さんたちが
日本で待ってるからね｡➡
Tamura and the other astronomers are waiting in Japan.
私も帰って
月面望遠鏡の計画を進めるわ｡
I have to go back and work on our plan to build the lunar telescope.
あ…ああ…｡
でも あんま無理はしないでよ
おばちゃん｡
Y-Yeah.
But don't work too hard, Aunt Sharon.
聞けば
せりかちゃんの お父さんも➡
Serika told me her father continued to research until he lost all ability to move.
体が動かなくなるギリギリまで
研究を続けたらしいのよね｡
私も見習って
行くとこまで行くわよ！
I'll follow his example, and do what I can.
＜医師は彼女に ちゃんと病気の
説明をしたのだろうか？➡
Did the doctors do a proper job of explaining her disorder?
She was so positive, I had to wonder.
そう疑うほど
シャロンは陽気だった｡➡
あと数ヵ月で シャロンは➡
In a few months, Sharon will no longer be able to play the piano anymore.
大好きなピアノも
弾けなくなってしまう｡➡
The doctors must have told her that.
その事を医師から
告げられているはずなのに…➡
それでも彼女は笑っていた＞
But she continued to smile.
シャロン！
Sharon!
It'll probably take three or four years before this will happen.
３年先か４年先か
わかんね～けど 俺の中じゃ➡
俺が誰より先に選ばれて
月で望遠鏡を建てる予定だよ｡
But I plan to be the first one chosen to go to the moon and build your telescope.
ありがと 楽しみにしてる｡
Thank you.
I can't wait to see it happen.
Hey, Aunt Sharon... Tell me something.
ねえ シャロンおばちゃん
教えて…｡
｢僕は いざという時
役にも立たない➡
How do I say, "I'm a useless person who always fails during crunch time," in English?
ダメ人間です｣って
英語で何て言うの？
何それ？そんなの訊いて
どうするの？
What's this about?
Why are you asking?
I'll need to know when I make friends in other countries.
いつか 外国の友達ができたら
言うんだよ｡
Since I'll probably be saying it all the time.
なんか俺 よく使いそうだから｡
何かあったの？
Did something happen?
Just tell me!
いいからぁ～ 教えてって！
Very well.
そうね…｡
今 ムッタが言った文の
英訳じゃないんだけど➡
This doesn't mean the exact same thing, but it's a simple phrase you can use.
もっとシンプルな
言い回しがあるわ｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)はい これ｡
Here you go.
え～と イッツ ア…｡
Uh, "It's..."
イッツ
ピース
オブ
ケイク
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)“It's a piece of cake"｡
It's a piece of cake.
ひと
それを直訳すれば｢ケｰキ一切れ分｣
って事になるんだけどね｡
And the phrase "piece of cake" also has a completely different meaning.
違う意味もあるのよ｡
なるほど…｢僕はケーキ
一切れ分の価値しかない➡
I get it...
It means I'm a useless human, worth less than a piece of cake.
あっけないダメ人間です｣
って意味か｡
ふふっ…まあ そうね｡➡
Something like that.
自由に使っていいわよ｡
Say that whenever you want.
現在
《料理…裁縫…文字を書く…➡
Cooking, sewing, writing...
細かな手作業から
できなくなっていく…か…》
It begins with the loss of any ability requiring hand coordination...
あ～ なんてヘタな字…｡
My handwriting's so ugly now.
何の根拠もなく
口から出まかせを…｡
I was lying out of my ass back there...
何が…
｢誰より先に月へ行く｣だよ！
I'll be chosen to go to the moon before anyone else?
シャロンを安心させるつもりで
あ～言ったんだろ？
Didn't you say that to comfort Sharon?
シャロンの別れ際の笑顔も
そ～いう事だろうよ｡
That's why she was smiling when she left.
ティー
さんぱち
俺 Ｔ－３８の筆記テストで
最低点だった…｡
I had the lowest score on the T-38 written test.
ここで出遅れた奴は
宇宙まで１０年待つって噂だ｡
I've heard you have to wait ten years to reach space if you fall behind here.
Huh?
Damn...
《チクショー…こんな大事な時に
結果を出せねぇ…》
I never produce results when I need them most!
I'm a useless person who always fails during crunch time.
《いざという時
役にも立たないダメ人間…！》
誰がどのタイミングでミｯションに
アサインされるのかは➡
Honestly, I have no idea how they decide when and who they assign to each mission.
正直 俺にも
わかんね～けどさ…➡
もし 筆記テストの点数順が
アサイン順になるってんなら➡
But if written test scores were a factor,
I doubt I'd have gotten to go to space.
俺はまだ
宇宙に行ってないと思わん？
Sharon's disease will rob her of the ability to use her hands and legs.
《シャロンの病気は いずれ
うば
シャロンの手足の自由を奪う》
She'll be able to hear, but not talk.
《耳は聞こえるけど
話せなくなる》
She'll be able to see,
《目は見えるけど まぶたを
開く事ができなくなってしまう》
but not to open her eyes.
《そうなる前に俺は…
見せられんのか!?》
Can I make it up there before that happens?
《シャロンの見たがってる
小惑星の姿を…!!》
To show her the asteroid she wants to see?!
Oh? Are you alone today, Nanba?
あれ？今日は
ひとりなんですか？南波さん｡
あ せりかさん…｡
Serika...
なんかまだ みんなでわいわい
食べれる気分じゃなくてさ｡
I'm not in the mood to eat with everyone right now.
わかります｡
I understand.
ていうか せりかさん
お昼 それ１個？
Wait, Serika...
Is that all you're having for lunch?
No, this is more along the lines of dessert...
え あ いや…
食後の別腹というやつです｡
“It's a piece of cake"って英語
使った事ある？せりかさん｡
Have you ever used the phrase, "It's a piece of cake"?
ん…いえ ないですけど
意味は知ってますよ｡
No, I haven't,
but I know what it means.
“楽勝だよ"って事ですよね｡
It means that something is easy, right?
そう…“楽勝だよ"｡
Yes, that it's easy.
昔 シャロンが 教えて
くれたんだけどさ この言葉｡
A long time ago, Sharon taught me that phrase.
I was actually requesting a self-derogatory English phrase.
でも そん時 本当は➡
もっとネガティブなセリフの
英訳を頼んだんだ｡そしたら…｡
But...
⦅“It's a piece of cake"⦆
It's a piece of cake.
って 堂々とウソを！
She lied.
まあ 本当の意味は
高校ん時に知ったワケだけど➡
Well, I learned the real meaning in high school.
But yeah...
それでも あれだ…
そ～いうウソなら➡
Sharon's the kind of person who's willing to lie in that situation.
平気でついちゃう人なんだよな
シャロンって…｡
月面望遠鏡の約束の事
シャロンさんから聞きましたよ｡
Sharon told me about your promise to build a telescope on the moon.
とうじょう
私がＩＳＳ搭乗を希望するのは➡
I want to board the ISS to be able to develop new treatments for incurable diseases.
難病に効く新薬開発に
こうけん
貢献するためです｡
特に…
私の父を苦しめたＡＬＳを➡
In particular, I wish to rid the world of ALS, the disease that took my father.
この世から
なくしてしまいたいんです｡
私も…シャロンさんと
約束したんです｡自信もないのに｡
I also made a promise to Sharon.
I'm not very confident...
シャロンさんの病気に効く薬を
私が生み出してみせるって｡
But I promised to develop a medicine to help treat Sharon's disease.
＜翌朝 シャロンから
メールが届いた＞
The next morning, I received an e-mail from Sharon.
｢無事 日本に到着です｡
私は明日から 張り切って➡
I made it back to Japan safely.
Starting tomorrow, I'll work on manuals for constructing a telescope on the moon.
月面望遠鏡の製作手順書を
作っていきます｡➡
So don't worry... Just focus on your training, Mutta.
私の事は心配しないで
訓練 頑張ってね ムッタ｡➡
私も ３年後か４年後かに…➡
In three or four years,
I plan to head over, to brief you on the lunar telescope project.
あなたに 月面望遠鏡計画の全ての
説明を伝えに行く予定です｡➡
覚えることだらけよ｡
覚悟はいい？｣｡
You'll have a lot to learn.
Are you prepared?
言ってくれるじゃないの ムッタ｡
That's the spirit, Mutta!
＜シャロンを
元気づけられるような文章は➡
After racking my brain for the words to cheer Sharon up,
考えても考えても生み出せず…➡
“ケーキ一切れ分"とだけ
返信した＞
I could only respond with a piece of cake.
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#65 Wheelchair Pilot
It's finally time for flight training on the T-38s.
＜いよいよＴ－３８の
操縦訓練が始まる＞
＜私の訓練教官として
現れたのは➡
And I end up with that old guy as my instructor.
あろうことか
あのじいさんだった！＞
Good to see you again, Mutta!
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)＜久しぶりだな ムッタ＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Wheelchair Pilot"